<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble petition offered to the right reuerend, honourable, and vvorshipfull estates of this present Parliament assembled ar [sic] Westminster Pallace wherein the wandring ghost of the late pyramis demolished lately in París, discourseth his hard fortunes, trauailes, and strange accidents to the new Brittaine monarchie, to whom he wisheth all peace, wealth, and prosperitie. Written by Philopatris, pittying his downfall, and perswading his new erecting, and building vp againe in Westminster.</title>
            <author>Philopatris, fl. 1606.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115283</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850502</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850502</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15710</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09609)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15710)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1181:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble petition offered to the right reuerend, honourable, and vvorshipfull estates of this present Parliament assembled ar [sic] Westminster Pallace wherein the wandring ghost of the late pyramis demolished lately in París, discourseth his hard fortunes, trauailes, and strange accidents to the new Brittaine monarchie, to whom he wisheth all peace, wealth, and prosperitie. Written by Philopatris, pittying his downfall, and perswading his new erecting, and building vp againe in Westminster.</title>
                  <author>Philopatris, fl. 1606.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Humphrey Lownes] for Matthew Lownes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An anti-Jesuit work.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: To the high Court of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Vertical chain lines.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  France --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15710:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15710:1"/>
            <p>AN HVMBLE Petition offered to the right reuerend, honourable, and vvorſhipfull eſtates of this preſent Parliament aſſembled at Weſtminſter Pallace: Wherein the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Ghoſt of the late Pyramis demoliſhed lately in Paris, diſcourſeth his hard fortunes, trauailes, and ſtrange accidents to the new Brittaine Monarchie, to whom he wiſheth all peace, wealth, and proſperitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by Philopatris, pittying his downfall, and perſwading his new erecting, and building vp againe in Weſtminster.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>At London Printed for <hi>Matthew Lownes.</hi> 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:15710:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15710:2"/>
            <head>To ancient and famous Troynovant.</head>
            <l>WIth ſunburnd Afrike Europe bore debate,</l>
            <l>And France with fertile Egipt did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend;</l>
            <l>With <hi>Memphis</hi> old <hi>Lutetia</hi> ſtroue of late,</l>
            <l>For Monuments; but now that ſtrife hath end:</l>
            <l>The <hi>Pyramies</hi> of Paris doo decay,</l>
            <l>But <hi>Memphis</hi> ſtones remaine &amp; ſtand for aye.</l>
            <l>Shall Afrike thus tryumph in Europes ſhame?</l>
            <l>Can <hi>Brittaine</hi> braue, endure ſo great diſgrace?</l>
            <l>No, Troynovant; flie thou on wings of fame,</l>
            <l>From <hi>Memphis</hi> both, and <hi>Paris</hi> take thou place:</l>
            <l>Build monuments, in ſpight of Popiſh fire,</l>
            <l>Which Afrike both, and Aſia may admire.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15710:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15710:3"/>
            <head>To the high Court <hi>of Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that my ſuddaine down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall &amp; vnexpected overthrow (moſt ancient and famous great <hi>Brittaine</hi>) was plotted ſecretly in <hi>Rome,</hi> prepared cunningly in <hi>France,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted ignominiouſly not long ſince by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique aucthoritie in the chiefe Cittie of the <hi>French</hi> Kingdome. This favour yet I had for my continuall and faithfull ſervice done to ſo great a King and State, that ſome of my dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friends and favourers (whoſe long plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in Lawe, ſtrong reaſons in equitie, and earneſt ſute in Court nothing prevailing for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15710:4"/>
the ſaving of my faultleſſe and innocent life) ſhould bee permitted at laſt after my death, to gather together the fatall reliques and ruines of my ſumptuous builded corps, to be ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid vp in ſome ſure place, there to be ſhrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto a better and more favourable age following, from the cruell perſecution of my bloudie Eſauiticall enemies, ſeeking and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing (like vnto <hi>Herod</hi> through all <hi>Iuda</hi>) from corner to corner for the anatomie of my bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bones, to be offred vp as a ſweete ſmelling ſacrifice to that Antichriſtian &amp; bloudie Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, who daily thirſteth for the poore lyues of ſuch harmleſſe creatures as I am, manifeſting to the world his foule ſhame, and monſtrous parts. But may it not ſeeme ouer-ſtrange and meruailous to the eyes and eares of the world, that dumbe and inſenſible creatures ſhould ſpeake and crie out of cruell iniuſtice vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them? Mervailous indeed it is, becauſe againſt nature, but not therfore vntrue nor yet vnlikely, conſidering what the Prophets haue truly fore-told, howe in the latter dayes there ſhould many miraculous thinges fall out, and wonderfull viſions appeare, both in heaven &amp; earth. And ſurely (thou new Monarchie) the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15710:4"/>
eclipſe of the Sunne ſeene here of late, with the new ſtarre, but more likelie a prodigious Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met in thy Hemiſphere, the extraordinarie red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the firmament like to bloud, the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall raines and land flouds, the monſtrous births of children, and beaſtes on the earth, and of fiſhes in the Sea; but more notable, that a new and vnknowne Aſtrologer in his Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtication ſet out in our Cittie of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſhould fore-ſhew ſuch ſtrange and incredible matters to come to paſſe, three moneths before this wonderfull accident was knowne among you, to wit, that this yeare 1605 heere ſhould bee a <hi>turbulent Parliament, a black Christmas, and a bloudie Lent.</hi> Did not all theſe things agreeing as it were, and conſpiring together ſpeake and fore-warne you (beloved great <hi>Brittaine</hi>) even as they had beene reaſonable creatures, of the great diſaſtre likely to fall out, comming to my eares. Mervaile not then, if I that had my ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction eſtabliſhed by the ſound adviſement and firme decree of the graveſt, wiſeſt, and moſt learned Parliament of the world, &amp; perfected by the ſacred influence and infuſion of all the Muſes through every member of my bodie, &amp; life given to mee by my Soveraigne King, to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15710:5"/>
witneſſe the ſafetie of his life, ſhould not as wel ſpeake, at leaſt my Ghoſt, as did the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet ſpirit of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and rather to bee better thought of, then it, becauſe both my warrant and cauſe is approovedly good. But while <hi>I</hi> ſtoode long time in a muſe, pondering betwixt hope and diſpaire, what ſhould become of my wandring ſoule, and at length, thinking with my ſelfe, to finde out ſome <hi>Pythagorean</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers (if anie were yet aliue) for conſulting, what bodie ſhould be fitteſt for my receptacle; certaine my loving friends in this time, inſpired (as the ſequell ſhall teſtifie) with ſome divine inſtinct, convayed me ſafely to great <hi>Brittaines</hi> Ocean Sea: where <hi>Neptune</hi> receaving me cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſlie at their hands, commaunded <hi>Aeolus</hi> with his faireſt and readieſt windes ſafelie and ſpeedilie to tranſport me from that dangerous ſhore I was on, to the famous <hi>Microcoſme</hi> of ancient <hi>Brittaine,</hi> the great Conquerour, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time of my ingrate Countrie, as to the chiefe harbour of all poore diſtreſſed Pilgrimes. But while <hi>Aeolus</hi> was preparing all things neceſſarie for my ſafe conduct, <hi>Neptune</hi> willed me, brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to report the cauſes of my ſuddaine flight and departure from my native Countrie,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15710:5"/>
which though at firſt <hi>I</hi> was in doubt what to doe, as fearing that hee might either bewray me to mine enemies, when <hi>I</hi> had told him all, or might ſtop my paſſage, if I told him not, at laſt I reſolved vpon all hazards that might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, to ſatisfie his demaund, as farre foorth, as the ſhortnes of the time, and perill of the place would permit. Then thus I ſpake vnto him. The cauſes that haue compeld mee (O great <hi>Neptune,</hi> thou great God of the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) to ſeeke thy favour in this my miſerie, are trulie and vpon my alleagiance vnto thee, the extreame and more then inhumane perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of my bloudie enemies the Ieſuites both before, and ſince my lamentable and vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved death &amp; overthrow, procured for no other cauſe, then for truly witneſſing to the world, but more particularly to true Catholique Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and to all forraine Strangers who might dailie beholde mee in the prime of my tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant eſtate, in the moſt famous Cittie and place of the vniuerſall world, how this mightie King &amp; martial Monarch <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, that now raigneth, was treacherouſly wounded, but yet miraculouſly preſerved of his life, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Eſauitical</hi> plot executed by <hi>Chattell</hi> one of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15710:6"/>
novices, trayned vp in their tragicall Schoole erected latelie for teaching of bloudie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, for the killing of all ſuch Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as being either Romaniſts or true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſhall be ſtumbling blocks to hinder the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick courſes of their new eſtabliſhed Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villian Government. <hi>Me miſerûm vox faucibus haeret</hi> I cannot vtter the one halfe I would ſay, ſuch haſt I haue to be gone for the feare &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger I am in, by the furious purſute of my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed enemies, who tyrannouſlie triumphing in mine overthrow, mangled all the members of my bodie as was pittifull to ſee, and yet not ſo ſatisfied, will not ſuffer my broken bones, no, nor my verie Ghoſt to remaine in reſt or ſafetie within anie part of this ample Kingdom. Theſe men (or to ſpeake more properly mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of men) being iuſtlie (and as deſervedlie, as ever anie the moſt haynous malefactors that ever were) banniſhed out of this Realme by a generall decree of Parliament, without hope of being ever recalled home, or to creepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into anie grace or favour of my great Soveraigne, which they had ſo foulely forfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are nowe againe (a wonder it is to heare) after a few yeares exile, come not ſubmiſſiuely,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15710:6"/>
but triumphantly home, glorying in the ſpoiles of my heauie and ſad fall; dying; and lying pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at their proud feete. And thus are they growne into great credite and aucthoritie by the diſtraction of my Soveraignes late ſingular favour towardes mee, which I ſurelie hoped, ſhould, nay could never haue been withdrawn, being ſo faſt tied and conglutinate to my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as a publique decree of the wiſeſt humane wits could deviſe, and ingraven beſides in let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Gold and Azure, for the more honour and ornament to vs both. But what ſhal I ſay, <hi>Nibi ſub coelo durabile, et Regum gratia ſaepe mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabilis:</hi> For my craftie enemies had ſo cloſed vp and ſtopped the princelie eares of my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne (which ſhould haue beene open alike to all Complayners) with a fine and ſubtil kind of black Cotton cunningly wrought by the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and moſt expert <hi>Eſauiticall</hi> Artificers that were in all <hi>Italie</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> who bore his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in hand, that my bruſed bones broken all to peeces would bee the moſt effectuall preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatiue for reſiſting all peſtilent venome of ſuch Hereticks, as ſhould oppoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt the wholeſome and ſound reeſtabliſhment of the Ieſuites, adding moreover (no ſmall falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15710:7"/>
that theſe would prooue heereafter the moſt profitable and ſerviceable people vnto him, that were vnder his obeyſance. So my dread Liege being fully poſſeſſed by little and little with the ſlie inſinuations of this counterfet Cotton, neither the credite of ſundrie of his faithfull Counſailors, neither the waightie ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of the moſt graue and iuditious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of his Parliament, nor the eloquence and ſmooth reaſons of learned Advocates, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſubtile inventions and ſcholaſtick So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtrie of the Sorboniſt Doctors, nor the pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious plaints of poore Schollers, who delighted their eyes, refreſhed their mindes, and filled their papers and bookes with the learned Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that guarded my ſquare bodie; all theſe my favourers, I ſay, and continuall interceſſours could prevaile nothing with my dread Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, whoſe pittie my enemies had captiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wholy to their crueltie and malice, that no place was left for prayers, nor meanes anie longer for my continuance there, but <hi>Diſcere dura pati,</hi> and comfort my ſelfe with that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement that vertuous <hi>Aeneas</hi> gaue to his Sea-beaten Souldiours. <hi>Durato et temet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſeruato ſecundis.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15710:7"/>Pluck vp thy heart, and driue from thee</l>
               <l>both care and feare away:</l>
               <l>To think of this, may pleaſure bee</l>
               <l>to thee another day.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thus remained then no other comfort to me, neare halfe dead before hand through di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, but that of neceſſitie (as I well percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) it behooved one to die for the ſinnes of this people, and who ſhould that be, but even <hi>I</hi> poore <hi>Pyramis,</hi> who not long before, had life with the promiſe of a long life, (but what mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men can promiſe life to another, that are not aſſured of their owne) given vnto mee, for recording their barbarous crueltie, and now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine muſt looſe my life, even in that place, alas, where <hi>I</hi> firſt receaved life, and for no other thing, then for teſtimonie of the truth, and to giue them a ſurer and longer life by my ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die death, and withall a greater honour and credit by my downefall, then ever they had ſince their firſt originall, or ever could hope for themſelues in this worlde. And thus is the worlde there turned topſie turvie: The good and faythfull are taken away, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15710:8"/>
and the wicked and vngratious are hoyſted vp in their roomes. <hi>O ſcelus, O mores, O tempora perverſa in quibus vixi.</hi> O poore and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wretch that I am, what haue I committed, that I ſhould ſuffer ſo cruell a puniſhment? <hi>I</hi> haue continued there but a ſmall time, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the eternitie of yeares <hi>I</hi> ſhould haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, erected alſo in the moſt eminent place of our Monarchie, to the amazement of my profeſſed enemies; where I indured dailie op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious railings and infamous Paſquils on my frontiſpice, taxing both King, Counſell, Parliament, and State for my ſumptuous buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in ſo famous a place, beſides my nightlie danger (for witneſſing the decree of their ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ſo infamous a fact) to be diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and by the Sturre &amp; tumults of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents pulled downe before the morrow, &amp; that not perchance without the ſhedding of innocent bloud. All this and much more it behooved me to indure, yea and much more would <hi>I</hi> patiently haue ſuffred, ſo as <hi>I</hi> might haue continued there, vntill <hi>I</hi> had either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved ſome recompence for my faithfull ſervice, or had beene beſtowed in ſome other famous place, to haue ſerved for a perpetuall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15710:8"/>
memorie of that infamous treacherie, that can never be forgotten.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nec tamen annoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeries, nec flamma, nec enſis,</l>
               <l>Aeternum poterit hoc abolere ſcelus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thus ending my diſcourſe to <hi>Neptune,</hi> and craving his favourable ayde for my paſſage to great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> my laſt and onelie refuge left vnto mee. The God ſmiling ſpake with a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious countenance vnto me, <hi>Fauet fortuna vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> And ſo by the favour of <hi>Aeolus</hi> and the ſwift winges of his windes, I was vpon the ſuddaine (before <hi>I</hi> could bethinke my ſelfe where <hi>I</hi> was) ſet vpon the white &amp; pleaſant <hi>Brittaine</hi> Coaſt, where vpon a greene mountaine, not far from the place of my arrivall, was firſt preſented to my view, a goodly companie of frollique Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, who as they drew ſomewhat neare me, caſt off their mourning garments, which they had worne (as ſeemed) before, for the great &amp; horrible daunger they apprehended by their long experience, knowledge, and inſight of the heavenlie conſtellations &amp; caeleſtiall ſignes, of ſome great fatall coniurations plotted by <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> and his Stygian furies, for the totall ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this ancient Kingdome and State, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15710:9"/>
were all preſentlie cloathed in white, playing and ſinging ſweete and melodious congratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, for the happie deliverie both of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Countrie from that great imminent perill, as alſo for my fortunate arrivall in ſo fit a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, wherby <hi>I</hi> might not onelie teſtifie to them my Countries crueltie, and her ingratitude towards mee, but that I might likewiſe in ſhort ſucceſſe of time eternize my name, by offering my ſervice in publiſhing by open teſtimonie both to the great and little World, a more hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and damnable fact, then before <hi>I</hi> ſerved for. And ſo being a little comforted and put in ſome good hope by this their newes, my faint ſpirit begins to take freſh courage, and to ſtrengthen my weake limbes, ſo that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to march a faſter pace, then before <hi>I</hi> was accuſtomed to, with deſire to learne more certaintie of this newes, which yet was a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie vnto me: and caſting mine eyes round about mee, to ſee if <hi>I</hi> could diſcerne anie thing, I perceaved betwixt mee and the skie, beeing then the dawning of the day (before <hi>Phoebus</hi> had ſent abroade his rayes for the clearing of the ayre with vniuerſall light) the whole companie of the ſacred Muſes ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15710:9"/>
with their ever flouriſhing greene Lawrel Garlands, who holding in their hands ſundry &amp; ſeverall inſtruments of muſique, made the hils, valleyes, and groues to reſound with their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly harmonie, melodious Songs, ſweet ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and ſhrill Ecchoes of their learned Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call inventions in all languages; and all this they did to ſignifie the exceeding ioy they had late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceaved of the thrice happie deliverance of that their great friend, darling, &amp; favourer, the moſt wiſe, prudent, learned, mightie, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, and in all heroicall vertues and valour, the moſt rare and great <hi>Apollo,</hi> whom <hi>Mars</hi> that ſterne God of bloudie battaile evermore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied and hated even to the death, for no other cauſe (as can bee coniectured, or as <hi>I</hi> could learne out of their rare Ditties and Sonnets) then onelie, for that he was entred into a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere league and ſweete ſocietie of the caele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall Graces, the devine Muſes, and ſacred Peace, (whereto hee was preordayned at the verie houre of his nativitie) and thereby, and by meanes of the common tranquillitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of enſuing, had brought and deduced from aboue, into this little world, &amp; from thence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to all the moſt famous parts of the great
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15710:10"/>
world, ſuch manifold and exceeding rich gifts, bounteous favours, and invaluable benefits &amp; bleſſings, as the like had either ſeldome, or not at all beene enioyed in anie former age, for which he was (as he well deſerved) vniuerſallie admired, honoured, and bleſſed over all. And therfore the greater indignation boiled in the breaſt of angrie <hi>Mars,</hi> who ever more grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at humane felicitie, left no meanes or waies vnſought or vnatte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted, whereby to bring our great Patron &amp; Benefactor, and conſequentlie this little world to confuſion. And ſuch was his innated hatred againſt him, even when he was yet in his Mothers bellie, knowing by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable aſpects of <hi>Sol</hi> &amp; <hi>Venus,</hi> that he ſhould proue a moſt potent, prudent, wiſe, &amp; bleſſed Prince of Peace, beloved both of Gods &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he this wicked <hi>Mars</hi> ſet on his cruell Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant the elder <hi>Gowrie</hi> to haue murdered that moſt noble <hi>Heroine</hi> the Queene his mother, &amp; this bleſſed fruit of her womb, at one ſtab. And being prevented by divine providence of his malignitie, in this his abhominable intention, after manie other miſchievous plots and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes (all of them, as all other ſhall ever be made fruſtrate by the high hand of iuſt <hi>Joue</hi>) he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15710:10"/>
with that variable <hi>Aeolus</hi> GOD of the windes (who either by faire meanes, or ſharpe menaces of anie great Power is lightlie wonne to worke the worſt miſchiefe he can) to giue full ſcope and free licence to his turbulent and vnrulie windes, at ſuch time, as our bright day-ſtarre <hi>Apollo</hi> having accompliſhed the notable ſolemnitie of thoſe famous nuptialls in the ſtrong <hi>Dacian</hi> Kingdome, the middle Region of <hi>Europa,</hi> with his peereleſſe Paragon, of all rich perfection the divine <hi>Cynthia</hi> (otherwiſe then by himſelfe immatchable) had imbarqued him with his moſt lovelie beloved above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſailing from thence through the Ocean, towards his ancient Kingdom the leſſer <hi>Albion,</hi> lying to the north of <hi>Albion maior,</hi> (now both by his Highnes happilie reduced to one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie) then was ſeene the boiſterous rage of bluſtring <hi>Boreas</hi> and his rude companions, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering with might and maine vncontroled in <hi>Neptunes</hi> maine dominion, (but without that great Gods aſſent or knowledge) as ſomtime by the like permiſſion of their flexible Maſter <hi>Aeolus</hi> at the requeſt of angrie <hi>Juno,</hi> they pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed the like peremptorie pranks (vnwitting to <hi>Neptune</hi>) vpon the vertuous and valorous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15710:11"/>
Prince <hi>Aeneas</hi> in the Tyrrhene Seas. So that colleaguing themſelues with that great Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſe <hi>Circe,</hi> and a great number of her moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious and deteſtable impes, all practiſing to drowne and deſtroy our <hi>Apollo</hi> and his faireſt <hi>Cynthia</hi> with all their noble traine (as after vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their conviction they freely confeſſed) they ſturdilie heaved, toſſed, and tumbled the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full billowes, hoyſing one while his drearie ſhips vpon the high-raiſed waues almoſt to the azure skie, and then throwing them downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine as lowe as the foundations of the earth. Yet notwithſtanding all their furious tumults, and violent commotions, Almightie <hi>Joue</hi> (whoſe name be therefore magnified for ever) beholding this outragious tempeſt, and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the wicked occaſion thereof; brought them ſafe and ſound to their own deſired con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent &amp; Country. Which, when <hi>Mars</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, he ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ped &amp; ſtared, foming at the mouth, and his eyes ſparkling like fire for verie anger, that his conſpiracie prevailed not, he fared like a mad man, and vowing ſtill to purſue him with immortall hatred, ſwore by the black river of <hi>Stix,</hi> that his day of <hi>Mars</hi> wheron he was born, ſhould ever proue the moſt fatall day of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto him. And for that purpoſe he combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15710:11"/>
himſelfe with <hi>Pluto</hi> that dreadful Prince of <hi>Erebus,</hi> who complotting together, brought it ſo to paſſe vnder cunning pollicies and faire ſhewes of great matters, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerned his own perſon, ſtate, and Kingdome, to bring him by the earneſt labour of one of his deare favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, to the diſhonourable and diſloyall houſe of the other Sergeant of <hi>Mars</hi> the younger &amp; laſt <hi>Gowry,</hi> the bloudie nephew of a cruel tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Grandſire, where having locked him vp in a cloſe roome in the hands of their ſworne friends, his mortal enemies, he had no way nor meanes to eſcape, but even miraculouſly by his own ſtout manhood, or rather Heroick magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, &amp; the ſuccour of a few of his faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, but chiefly againe by the almightie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of high <hi>Joue,</hi> waiting over him, at all times and places for his ſafeguard, hee was alſo delivered out of that danger. Then were <hi>Mars</hi> &amp; <hi>Pluto</hi> more enraged then ever before, gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing their teeth, and curſing and banning the fiends and furies, that had no more pollicie or power to accompliſh their infernall plot, they were almoſt at a point to haue giuen over anie lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger purſuit of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracies, but that <hi>Pluto</hi> bethought himſelfe of his deare ſon the red &amp; bloudy Dragon, who throgh long &amp; continual
practiſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15710:12"/>
for manie ages, of all ſorts of helliſh ſtratagems, horrible maſſacres, blacke murders, deceitfull lies, and falſe miracles was growne to bee as much famed and feared in the world, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo as it might be a queſtion diſputable in Schooles, whether Sathan the roaring and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Lyon, or his ſonne the Pope, that red &amp; bloudie Dragon was to be held for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and chiefeſt lier and murtherer. <hi>Pluto</hi> therefore crying out, <hi>Flectere ſi nequeo ſuperos, Acheronta mouebo,</hi> they began to be recomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his deare ſonne, of their wicked hopes &amp; divelliſh drifts for the acting of their bloudie Tragedie, (as the laſt hope of all their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes). And ſo adioyning themſelues to this other great enemie of mans welfare, who was exceeding proude to haue the mannaging of that action referred to him, wherein the Prince of Devils had failed, conceaued preſently a more horrible plot, then all the Stygian furies called together in a common Counſell could haue deviſed, not onely againſt the ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon &amp; life of <hi>Apollo,</hi> but alſo his divine <hi>Cynthia,</hi> and all their Godlike progenie, &amp; all the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes, Prelates, Nobles, Stateſmen, and chiefe Gentrie vnder his Domination; all whom, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15710:12"/>
manie moe, by force of his invention, he made ſure account to haue deſtroyed vpon that omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous day of <hi>Mars,</hi> with one blow of his fatall engine. Which complot hee gaue in charge for the more ſuretie to certaine of his truſtie Enginers the <hi>Eſauiticall</hi> band (whoſe charge, profeſſion, and practiſe, is nothing elſe but the vndermining and blowing vp of Princes, great States, and Kingdomes) to ſee the ſame with all ſecret conveyance and diligence put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution. Never before was heard of, the like inhumane ſtratagem, though manie cunning &amp; cruell conſpiracies proceeding from this terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Dragon, had often been attempted againſt our <hi>Apolloes</hi> Predeceſſour, his moſt honoured and hallowed virgin ſiſter, the great &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>Diana,</hi> whom hee moſt maliced and hated deadlie aboue anie other Potentate on the earth, for that ſhe as a moſt vertuous and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious Princeſſe, and Faiths valorous Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pioneſſe, had not onelie given to him a wide &amp; dangerous wound, that ſtill, &amp; ſtill ſhall ever to his dying day put him to moſt grievous paine; but alſo deſtroyed a great number of miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous monſters that were conceaved and crept forth out of his foule mouth. All his practiſes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15710:13"/>
notwithſtanding, and though he did the verie worſt he could, could nothing prevaile againſt her moſt bleſſed life, raigne, ſtate, &amp; governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that for 44 yeares together and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, while ſhe ruled the famous Kingdome of <hi>Albion maior,</hi> to the high pleaſure of Almighty <hi>Joue,</hi> a more flouriſhing and bleſſed eſtate was there ſeene, then was ever heard of in thoſe times, when divine <hi>Astraea</hi> lived and ruled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong earthly men. And in this meane time, while as the Almightie God perceaving this earthly Kingdome of her moſt happie and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Maieſtie, to bee compaſſed and clogged with ſo many daily conſpiracies and dangers, and that her ſacred perſon having by the due courſe of nature runne out, &amp; ended the glaſſe of her thrice happie and moſt renowmed go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; than it pleaſed him in his great and loving favour and mercie (moſt happily and peaceably without anie danger or diſturbance to her well long governed Kingdomes) to tranſlate her hence to the higheſt Emperiall heaven, there to live and raigne in the greateſt glorie with his Angels to all eternitie. Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting in her place this our <hi>Apollo,</hi> whom hee hath predeſtinated to vanquiſh, and finally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15710:13"/>
this monſtrous red Dragon, whereby he ſhall purchaſe ſo much the greater glorie and immortall renowme to himſelfe, then did the olde <hi>Apollo,</hi> by killing the huge ſerpent <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon,</hi> by how much this Dragon is a thouſand folde more great, virulent, violent, terrible, ſtrong, and horrible then that was. This is the great cauſe indeede, why <hi>Mars</hi> fretteth, <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> fumeth, the Dragon rageth, and all iointlie conioyne and conſpire with all their forces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the life and ſtate of <hi>Apollo,</hi> for whoſe moſt happie preſervation from all their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded miſchiefes; the melodious Muſes ſang <hi>Jo Pean,</hi> with manie heavenlie notes (ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter farre then the concentfull harmonie of the ſphericall Orbes) full of ioy and tryumph. But reſerving the reſidue of the rareſt and ſecreteſt matter of their divine ſongs, vntill <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſee the end of my travailes, I will briefelie ſhewe, what further befell mee. Thus being heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſomewhat more confirmed of the trueth of ſo woonderfull newes, and advauncing my ſteps forward to ſee the end and ſucceſſe of theſe ſtrange incounters, <hi>I</hi> caſt my ſleepie eyes here &amp; there (the day being all ſpent, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15710:14"/>
blacke and raynie clouds covering the bright ſtarres in the firmament) when loe in an inſtant, there appeared to me, as it were Vulcan in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erie ſparkes &amp; ſhining flames of great burning fires, environing me on all parts, where I went. I miſdoubting at firſt, that <hi>Vulcan</hi> and <hi>Pluto</hi> had conſpired the burning of the whole Iſland I was entred into, reſolved with my ſelfe (if it were poſſible) to returne and eſcape ſo great and imminent a danger. But being ſoone ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed, that the matter was nothing ſo, as I ſuppoſed, but that theſe fires were kindled on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for ioy, according to the commendable cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of this Iſland, when any good newes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth to the State, or Countrie: Behold, I was no ſooner rid of this feare and perplexitie, but that <hi>I</hi> might ſee three ſeverall Currors of ſundrie nations (as appeared by their cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances on their breſt) going for <hi>France, Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Jtalie,</hi> and ſeemed to bee verie paſſionate and ſad by their countenance and cariage, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were for the ill ſucceſſe of the plot then diſcovered, or for that they feared, the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were all ſtopt, ſo as they could not giue the firſt advertiſement to their Maiſters, <hi>I</hi> leaue them to your good and friendly conſideration
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15710:14"/>
(great <hi>Brittaine</hi>) who can better iudge in their matters, and tell by the Weathercocke what quarter the wind holdeth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>I</hi> poore Pilgrime. Yet thus farre I can ſay of them, that their cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie and favour was ſuch to me a poore ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that they could not afford me one <hi>Aue,</hi> but making ſighes, and croſſes vpon their faces and breaſts, looked and beckened ſo on me, as to a Hugonet. But <hi>I</hi> ſore fearing, that they had beene Sergeants at armes ſent after me for my apprehenſion, where ſoever they might finde me, was glad to make a low curtſie, and paſſe by them, with as much ſpeed as my wearie feet could carie mee, and having poſted a mile fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (without once looking backe) It was my good hap to meete with two Engliſh Poſtes, bearing the red rampant Lyon on their breſts; who were ſo full of indignation, as that after my double ſalutations, they could not for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſpeake vnto me, and ſhewing a ſad &amp; ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull countenance, whither it were, that the ſtranger Poſtes had got the ſtart of them, or fearing that thorough favour they might get paſſage before them, to carrie the firſt newes to their Maiſters, and other forraine Princes, or for what other cauſe <hi>I</hi> know not, nor was it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15710:15"/>
fit for me, being a ſtranger and a banniſhed Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grime to be <hi>nimis curioſus in aliena republica.</hi> Yet ſtaying, and viewing one another more nearlie, <hi>I</hi> began to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber my ſelfe, that I had ſeene theſe two Engliſh Poſtes oftentimes not onely paſſe by me in their going to the Pallace of <hi>Paris,</hi> but that they had bin alſo accuſtomed theretofore, in pointing out their fingers to me, as to a rare myracle, to ſhew to their Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie men newly come over, my whole Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, birth, &amp; memorable ſtorie: And on the other ſide, one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being well travaild in all Countries, by his imployment in the ſervice of the late renowned Queene your Ladie, &amp; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven withall to the obſervations of antiquities abroad, drew out his bookes of thoſe matters, which hee ever caried about him into forraine parts, and turning the leaues over, he finds the whole diſcourſe of my life, which pondering to and fro in his mind, he begins to looke on mee more nearly &amp; circumſpectly, &amp; (the architec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of my ſtately building being yet freſh in his memorie) he fell ſomwhat to bleſſe himſelfe, &amp; after to craue pardon of the overſight, (as hee ſaid) of his duty to me, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had receaved ſo many curteſies for his Country me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; other
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15710:15"/>
ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers while <hi>I</hi> ſtood aliue, &amp; in credit with the great Princes &amp; Peeres of the Realm of <hi>France,</hi> then both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a laughing countenance ſtriving which of them ſhould firſt embrace &amp; welcom me, were ſo aſtoniſhed at my preſence, as they ſtood in doubt, whither they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce at my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming over, or lament for my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile and hard fortune, I was fallen into. But yet vpon better adviſe, they reioyced rather, that it had pleaſed the mightie <hi>Jehouah,</hi> to bring me ſafe into this famous Iſland, and that I had arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the beſt opportunitie, that ever could haue beene wiſhed, affirming that Gods great and miraculous providence was ſo favourable vnto me, that wheras my ſworne &amp; cruell <hi>Eſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall</hi> enemies hoped to haue triumphed in my late down-caſt, &amp; conſequently haue buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in everlaſting oblivion, they ſhould now be fruſtrate of their vngodly hopes, ſaying thus vnto me. Be of good comfort renowned <hi>Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</hi> thou ſhalt bee more welcome to this our newe Monarchie, then were thy enemies to their home-caller and reſtorer; and whereas thou wert permitted there to ſtande ſcarce the ſpace of the fourth part of an age, in thy glorious Trophee, as a witneſſe of two teeth ſtrucken out of the mouth of the Lordes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15710:16"/>
annointed, and for preſerving one King, which their novice and parricide <hi>Chattell</hi> had inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to haue killed, and for putting but one Kingdome in danger of forfaiture to the Pope their Creator, which before in colour of a falſe preſuppoſed right, hee pretended he had given to the holy Leaguers, and their coniured adherents, by excommunicating that your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Monarch; we doubt not, but heere thou ſhalt ſhortly ſerue for a greater vſe, and more glorious end, to bee erected as a witneſſe and perpetuall Record of the wonderfull &amp; thrice happie deliverie of our great and ſacred King the rareſt &amp; moſt learned King that ever bare Scepter either in this Iſland, or in any age pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or paſt; of his moſt gratious Queene that ſhall be by the loving favour of the Almightie, the ioyfull and bleſſed mother of many Kings &amp; Queenes; his tender &amp; deare ſonne &amp; heire, a Prince of the greateſt hope of his age; the reſt of his royall Progenie, all the reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, graue Counſailours, and Iudges, all the ancient Nobility, Gentillity, &amp; Burgeſſes cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and deputed for Commiſſioners to a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Parliament, and of many thouſand moe that were attendant to that ſolemnity, and of a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15710:16"/>
number of forraine Embaſſadours, if they had come thither, as was ſuppoſed, they ſhould; All theſe, and many moe, which were all in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to haue beene blowne vp, by a falſe and cruell Foxe, (for ſo was his name) ſent forth out of ſome of the Popes dennes, or rather <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toes</hi> dungeons, to kill, rent, and blow vp all the innocent &amp; ſimple ſheepe of Chriſtes Fold, in this new eſtabliſhed Monarchie, at one blow. This was one of the Popes Cannons, that hath been making this yeare &amp; halfe, by his fineſt &amp; moſt ſubtile-pated Artificers, which he had hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for this horrible worke of his, and this blow ſhould haue beene given by ſuch a ſmall Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, that was charged with no more then 34 great barrels of pouder, and with 24 ſtone of gad Iron for her bullet. All the thundring Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nons forged &amp; made in the bloudie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Trent</hi> were not ſo dangerous, as this one was. And yet true it is, that a few of theſe Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of <hi>Trent</hi> blew vp in <hi>Paris</hi> in one night, &amp; one morning tenne thouſand people, beſides 20000 they blewe vp in other Townes a little after, where one barrell of powder furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed all thoſe Cannons. But the greateſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence was this, they there killed but thouſands
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15710:17"/>
of poore Hugonets, but heere they aymed their murdring ſhot againſt King, Queene, Prince, Dukes, Earles, Barons, Prelates, Counſailours, Iudges, and Gentillitie of the Land; there they preſerved Houſes, Pallaces, Chappels, and Schooles; but here they would haue blowne vp the moſt ſtatelie buildings, Churches, Pallaces, and Schooles that pertained to the Crown, yea the treaſure and Records of the Kingdome; there they ſpoiled the living onely, but heere they would haue burnt and blowne vp the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and dead bodies of the famous Kings, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours, Queenes, &amp; Princes, ſleeping in their ſumptuous Toombs, as the rich and coſtly beds of their laſt honours they had heere vpon the earth. There they imagined by killing of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and wounding the fourth <hi>Henry,</hi> to haue wrought the overthrow &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of one ancient Kingdome; but here of three ſeverall moſt ancient and warlike King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of Chriſtendome. But having not lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſtand on more particulers, what ſhall <hi>I</hi> ſay to thee (O thou thrice happy exiled <hi>Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis</hi>) of theſe their never before invented cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties. <hi>Talia horret meminiſſe animus.</hi> O this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked treacherie, and falſe periurie of theirs! O
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15710:17"/>
cruell conſpiracie, and Graecian perfidie! O Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanicall enimitie, &amp; more then Neronian cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie! O Scythian barbarity, and Iudaiſme infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity! O Gentiliſme vanity, &amp; more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh impietie! and finally, O poyſoned Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall idolatry of theirs, proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their blind &amp; deviliſh devotion, the ground of their abhominable &amp; helliſh treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The treacherous conſpiracie of wicked <hi>Ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon</hi> that he wrought againſt the Iewes, to haue had them all killed in one day, whereſoever they ſhould be found in the vaſt Dominions of the great Monarch <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable to this: Nor the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie of <hi>Mithridates,</hi> who in one night &amp; a day killed thirtie thouſand Romanes: Nor the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie of wicked <hi>Nero</hi> who killed his mother, his maſter, &amp; that burnt almoſt whole <hi>Rome</hi> the chiefe Citie of the world, with a number of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cruelties that hee committed: Nor the bloud-thirſtie mind &amp; wicked deſire to raigne of <hi>Caligula,</hi> who wiſhed the whole Senate and chiefe men of the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, to haue had but one necke, that hee might haue ſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it off at one blowe: Neither the ſecret and bloudie conſpiracie of treacherous <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiline,</hi> who had privilie plotted not onelie the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15710:18"/>
death of the whole Senate, and chiefe men of name in <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo had deſtinated the moſt of his owne kindred to that cruell ſlaughter: Neither the damnable <hi>Sicilians</hi> evening ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices committed by them vpon the <hi>French</hi> men: Nor the Mattens of <hi>Paris</hi> performed by the <hi>French</hi> themſelues in maſſacring their owne Country men and deareſt friends, can in no degree be matched with this vnnaturall cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of theirs. And which is moſt ſtrange how it could be, all this their whole pernitious &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable enterpriſe of our tyrannous Traytors and cruell bloud-ſucking Papiſts, that had been more then a yeare in hatching, was ſo cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie &amp; ſecretly contrived and mannaged by the ſubtill and Machiavillian practiſes of ſome few maleconted Gentlemen ioyned to the Ieſuites and Seminarie Prieſts, who had the chiefe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment for matters both of Counſell &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, that it was brought forward vnknown &amp; vnrevealed even to the ſpace of a verie few houres, before the time of putting the ſame in execution; &amp; according to the relation of the chiefe Counſailours of our Eſtate, if the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God had not miraculouſly made our gratious Soveraigne, by divine inſpiration ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15710:18"/>
then by humane wiſedom and fore-ſight, to cauſe diligent inquirie to bee made of ſuch ſuſpect places of the Parliament houſe, as his Maieſtie greatlie miſdoubted after the reading of a miſticall &amp; ſtrange letter, out of the which, his Highnes collected &amp; apprehended more, then a great part of his Counſell could, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe this monſtrous contrived treaſon would haue ſorted to that wicked deſtinated event. Therefore O glorious, wiſe, and ever famous King, preſerved wee hope, for a greater worke of God, that by thy providence and ſacred ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences haſt ſaved thy ſelfe, thy ſucceſſion &amp; Kingdomes, a worke which time and memorie ſhall never deface, but ſhall be eternized to the worlds end, to thy immortall glorie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme. But O thou mightie <hi>Iehouah,</hi> to whom the higheſt glorie ſhall be aſcribed, that ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly haſt preſerved thy own annointed, and with him thy deare Church, which was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed with ſuch incomparable daunger that never was heard of before, neither was ever hatched the like by all the curſed brood of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, vntill this never before expected wicked time. Thus ending his tragicall diſcourſe, <hi>I</hi> became ſo aſtoniſhed and amazed thereat, as I
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15710:19"/>
became ſpeechleſſe, and as halfe dead, vntill theſe Currors began friendly to comfort mee: aſſuring mee, that the Almightie of his great providence had brought me here, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as my enemies the Ieſuites &amp; Seminary Prieſts, and their bloudie aſſociates and followers, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to haue gotten credit and eternall repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by the downe-caſt of me poore <hi>Pyramis</hi> at home in <hi>Paris,</hi> that now <hi>I</hi> ſhould be in a ſure way of preferment, by the gratious aſſiſtance of the moſt High, and the favour and pietie of the great, mightie, and religious Monarch, and this eſtate of the new Monarchy, &amp; little world, to receaue heere a greater glorie and honour by my newe erection in ſo famous an ancient Countrie, and place, then the diſgrace <hi>I</hi> had in <hi>France</hi> by my overthrowe: and that where my enemies intended to haue raced out vtterly all remembrance of me, they ſhould make me <hi>Jp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis invidis etiam nolentibus,</hi> to be more renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned then ever <hi>I</hi> was before, and more infamie to redound to them in the ſucceeding ages, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did to <hi>Eraſtratus</hi> that made himſelfe infamous to this day, by burning that rare &amp; ſumptuous temple of <hi>Diana</hi> in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> held for one of the ſeaven mervailes of the world; and whereas I had continued there ſcarce the quarter of a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15710:19"/>
mans age, they hoped, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſtand heere and, indure to the worlds end: &amp; whereas <hi>I</hi> was builded there in the ruines of a Merchants houſe, that heere I ſhould be erected in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of <hi>Plutoes</hi> deſtinated Pallace, to ſtand as a witneſſe of their damnable plot for the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ruine &amp; downefall of many hundred faire houſes of Nobility &amp; Gentrie: and that where my erection was there decreed by one Court of Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> conſiſting only of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents &amp; Lawyers, that here I ſhould be ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; confirmed by the Soveraigne Monarch, and three Eſtates of Parliament, ſolemnlie to ſtand in Amphitheatrick forme, after the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Romane manner. PROPTER REGEM, REGNVM, ET SVBDITOS SERVATOS. <hi>For preſerving the King, Kingdom, &amp; Subiects,</hi> in that ſame place where the fact &amp; cruell conſpiracie was intended to haue beene put in execution. And thus having diſcourſed vnto me this ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge conſpiracie, (of all conſpiracies that ever were the moſt capitall) &amp; incouraged me vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of my advancement, they courteouſlie took their leaues, after they had directed me to the famous Abbey of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> whitherward I hied me faſt, that there I might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among the graues of the dead, therby to
move
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15710:20"/>
all zealous and well affected <hi>Brittaine</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of all the three States in Parliament, that deteſt the crueltie of ſo great &amp; horrible a crime, &amp; hate the miſchievous plotters of ſuch haynous treaſon, to be interceſſors and petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners to their dread Soveraigne, for my erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and advancement to the Office of High Recorder of the preſervation of this new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie of great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> and that place no longer to be a Parliament-houſe, that was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to <hi>Pluto</hi> and his infernall Furies, but that I may ſucceede thereto, (after that it ſhall by a generall decree bee caſt downe) as a iuſt demoliſher of that Stygian field. <hi>I</hi> ſay no more now for very faintnes, but <hi>Miſericordia Dei ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per omnia opera,</hi> giving thankes in the meane time to the Author of my firſt life, and to him next, whoſoever he be, that hath preſerved my reliques and broken bones to ſo happy a time, thereby to giue me a ſecond life, as if <hi>I</hi> were a new <hi>Phoenix</hi> riſing out of my burnt aſhes, to make the world hereafter wonder at, &amp; deteſt more and more the crueltie of the Pope that bloudy Dragon, and his diveliſh children, and from terrifying ſuch miſcreants ever hereafter in any age ſubſequent, to attempt the like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15710:20"/>
the Lords annointed &amp; his Church, fully perſwading my ſelfe, that this great worke of the Lord in diſcovering ſo horrible a fact, by which, they promiſed to themſelues a finall &amp; infallible overthrow of Chriſts Church, and true religion in this Iſland, ſhall be the meanes by Gods wonderfull favour &amp; iudgement, that out of this Iſle ſhortlie ſhal march that mightie and fearefull Lyon, that beares in his Scutchion that martiall poeſie <hi>Parcere ſubiectis, et debellare ſuperbos,</hi> who ſhall overthrowe the bloudie Dragon, that Antichriſtian beaſt, with all his whelps in his devouring denne, and ſhall eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh Gods word there, which they purpoſed to haue extinguiſhed heere. And I thinke verily, that this is their laſt blow, that ever they ſhal be able to ſtrike, and which by the reverberating force of it ſhall be the moſt dangerous &amp; dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to themſelues, &amp; for their owne overthrow, yea ſorer then <hi>Luthers,</hi> that was the greateſt wound that the Romiſh Antichriſtian Church receaved in our memorie, and which (as <hi>I</hi> truſt) ſhall drive them in time to acknowledge their wickednes and blindnes, and to embrace the true faith in humilitie, and to craue me pardon for my downe-caſt and banniſhment from my
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15710:21"/>
native Countrie. And thus having made rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thee (O renowned Monarchie of great <hi>Brittaine</hi>) both of my paſſed and preſent for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and of the ſtrange accidents that haue hitherto happened vnto me, <hi>I</hi> implore thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ayde &amp; accuſtomed bountie never deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to any oppreſſed ſtranger, in vouchſafing to become an earneſt interceſſor for me, to the high &amp; moſt ſacred Maieſtie of thy great Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign (in whoſe potencie, &amp; your authority, the hope not onely of my preferment, but the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain accompliſhment of all thoſe great matters before ſpoken of, aſſuredly conſiſteth) that I may be receaved and brought to the preſence and moſt comfortable favour of his princely mercies, that by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I may haue a new life brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed into me, and be preferred to that eminent place, where <hi>I</hi> may beſt performe (as dutie and thankfulnes ſhall binde me) both to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and thy excellencie, that worthie and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervice, that ſhall neuer be but exceedingly well thought, &amp; highly comended to all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And to my auſpitious mind, no fitter place for demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtration of my dutifull ſeruice (I ſpeak not I proteſt out of ambition, or anie vicious humor) can be aſſigned me, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Parliament
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15710:21"/>
houſe, which theſe Monſters of mankinde, the Pope &amp; his miſcreant crue had meant to haue ſubverted &amp; demoliſhed by <hi>Plutoes</hi> &amp; <hi>Vulcans</hi> violent and boyſtrous fires &amp; flaſhing thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts, and ſo to haue made &amp; conſecrated it as a ruinous &amp; fit Pallace for the habitation of the black infernall Prince, &amp; his damned ſpirits and Miniſters of darknes. But that <hi>I</hi> may with the greater right, and without cavill of curious or captious heads ſtand there aucthorized, Let me alſo requeſt this favour at your handes (moſt mightie Monarchie) to move &amp; ſtir vp the wel affected mindes &amp; fierie zeales of the States of your Parliament, that at the next Seſſion, <hi>I</hi> being as yet but an Alian heere, may by Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute &amp; decree be naturalized, and infranchized as a borne ſubiect within your territorie, &amp; ſo thereafter to be erected and ſtand in the place that was deſtinated for <hi>Plutoes</hi> Pallace, as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall monument and Record of this horrible conſpiracie, &amp; of thine, &amp; our Monarchs moſt happy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſervation, &amp; as a caveat to the ages fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of the Papiſtical treaſons of the Romiſh Church, which I hope ſhall ſhortly inferre an end to that long vſurped tyrannicall raigne. And ſo perſwading my ſelfe, that if neither
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15710:22"/>
my poore and pittious diſtreſſed eſtate; neither the fine eloquence of the banniſhed <hi>Pyramis</hi> it ſelfe, ſpeaking to you in his owne <hi>French</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: newly ſet forth in your owne tongue, cannot perſwade you to immortalize your own deliverie from the greateſt apparant daunger that ever befell to you. I ſay, if this above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned reaſon, cannot move you to teſtifie in ſome meaſure, the earneſt deſire you haue to make this notable deliverie of GOD to bee knowne to the ages ſubſequent by my publike erecting again in a glorious <hi>Pyramis,</hi> by teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your inward tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes to him by this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward monument for your preſervation: Yet <hi>I</hi> beſeech you, although I ſeem perchance a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in outward ſhew, ſuffer me nevertheleſſe as a loving Patriark &amp; ſimpathizing Chriſtian, in the common cauſe, that theſe two great &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derfull works of the Almightie God, (may at leaſt move and touch your hearts, from the higheſt degree to the loweſt, from the head to the bodie, and ſo to all the members of this your Monarchie) I meane his great mercie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you all, and his fearefull iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your enemies in this never to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thrice happie and admirable deliverie. His
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15710:22"/>
mercie, <hi>I</hi> ſay, appeares not onely in diſcoverie of your danger, but in diſappointing of their cruell Parricide, and in preſerving your lyues from the ſnares of the bottomleſſe Locuſts of helliſh <hi>Babilon,</hi> his iudgement againe in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part is to be admired, in ſuffering a great part of them to bee apprehended, and made a perpetuall ſpectacle to all poſteritie, by a iuſt and moſt ſevere puniſhment, and the chiefeſt of them to haue ſuffered that ſame crueltie of puniſhment, by Gun-powder, which they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for your death.<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed therefore be the Lord of Hostes in all his workes, for his mercies be everlaſting, and his iudgements vnſearchable.</hi> And let this againe be your morning and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſacrifice, recommended to all Chriſtians <hi>of mercie and of iudgement both, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>my ſong ſhall bee:</hi> But if all this cannot perſwade you to erect mee for a publique Monument of your deliverie, yet let the godlie example of <hi>Abraham, Jſaack</hi> &amp; <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſtir you vp to this, who in their often deliveries &amp; favours recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the hands of God, erected both Altars and Monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of ſtones, as witneſſes of Gods ineſtimable favours &amp; bleſſings towards them, to their poſteritie; and ſeeing alſo that, that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15710:23"/>
Monument of publique prayers religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie ordained by his ſacred Maieſtie to bee celebrated through all his Kingdomes, for ſtirring vp of all mens affections in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to GOD, appeares almoſt in the verie beginning to bee neglected, both in Court, Countrie, and Citie; at leaſt permitte then the erection of this temporall and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Monument, to bee an occaſion and a meanes not onelie to lifte vp your externall eyes to GOD, but alſo rather to lift vp the eyes of your mindes and hearts to the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of GODS mercie towardes you all, and of his iudgement vpon your enemies. <hi>I</hi> could ſpeake farre more in this ſo ample and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Subiect, if I ſhould not bee thought too forward in ſo good a cauſe: but howſoever I, or the <hi>Pyramis</hi> that hath made mee thus to ſpeake bee liked of, ſo that I haue preſerved my ſelfe farre from <hi>Joue et fulmine,</hi> I care the leſſe the cenſure of the rude, and vnlearned that knowes not, but <hi>extra crepidam,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would I wiſh the covetouſneſſe of the rich, nor the envie of the malecontent, nor the partialitie of the indifferent, neither the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15710:23"/>
favourer of Poperie, hinder ſo good a worke, neither diſlike of mee the Patronizer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: adding onelie this ſhort caveat, with your good leaue and friendlie favour, that if the leaſt countenaunce of clemencie ſhall bee ſhowne to the Romaine conſpiratours and their aſſociates, either nowe or heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: it is to bee feared, that your clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſhall bee called crueltie, and your cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage cowardneſſe, and your loue hatred: And laſt of all, your Religion and Zeale to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Chriſtes Church and your Countrie, ſhall bee thought Atheiſme and Poperie. Which GOD forbid ſhould ever come to paſſe in ſuch a Chriſtian and flouriſhing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, where Chriſtes word is ſo vniuerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie &amp; religiouſlie preached. And if that you ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaue any of the greateſt or meaneſt ſort of thoſe coniured Traytours that bee nowe in hands; but eſpeciallie the Ieſuites and Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Prieſts, the chiefe inventours of all thoſe peſtilent plots, &amp; ringleaders of the reſt to this damnable Rebellion, either for feare, favour, or for anie other worldlie or politick reſpect: <hi>I</hi> feare not onely all ſuch that feares God truly at home, but all ſincere and faithfull Chriſtian
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15710:24"/>
neighbours abroad ſhall ſuſpect you as betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers both of Chriſtes Church, his true religion, your gratious King, Countrie, yea your owne lyues, to your verie enemies: and to this end ſurelie the eies and eares of all thoſe which be bound by the band of Vnitie in true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all forraigne Kingdomes, are bent to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and heare of the good ſucceſſe of ſo great a worke, put in your hand at this time; ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading themſelues in this meane time, that ſeeing it had pleaſed God to haue bleſt you by all other Nations and Kingdomes of the earth, with ſo wiſe, learned, and religious a King, ſo graue, godlie, expert, &amp; foreſeeing a Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wherein I wiſh, <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>Davids</hi> zeale, <hi>Jonathans</hi> faithfulnes, <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuahs</hi> courage, and <hi>Judiths</hi> ſpirit and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may appeare in everie one of you at this preſent, having alſo ſo faithfull and obeyſant Magiſtrates and Subiects to execute, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever your ſacred King and three Eſtates ſhal decree in this preſent Parliament, expecting in this meane time at your hands, ſuch godlie, neceſſarie, and ſtrict lawes, with their due exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution without delay &amp; acception of perſons, as Chriſtes Church and true religion, may be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15710:24"/>
without all feare of danger; and on the other part the Papiſts your enemies, may be in ſuch ſure guard, with a care to diſarme them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them of all ſuch meanes whatſoever, as in anie way heereafter may giue but the leaſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition of anie thing, that may indanger his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſucceſſion, &amp; Kingdoms, either by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues heere at home, or otherwiſe abroad, by their favourers and aſſociates. And ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with thy ſelfe (beloved great <hi>Brittaine</hi>) the ſinguler goodnes of thy God towards thee, and thine annointed King, in delivering you both (who were appointed as Sheepe to the ſlaughter) from that moſt barbarous &amp; ſavage imminent maſſacre, and vnnaturall conſpiracie (no age ever yeelding example of like cruelty) &amp; that thy deliverie &amp; ſafetie came not of thy merit, but of Gods great mercie, not thy fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, but his providence, not thy loue to God, but his to thine annointed King and his choſen people. Forget not therefore, to praiſe, thank, and glorifie the Lord of Hoſtes continuallie, for his mervailous and moſt mercifull work of thy preſervation and ſafetie, for his mercie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for ever. Which that thou, and thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people, and their ſeed after them, may not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15710:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
onelie the better remember and be taught to doe, but learne alſo to abhorre the odious hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſnes of ſo foule a fact: Let it be (as it is moſt worthie to be) written and engraven in my Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of laſting Marble <hi>ad perpetuam rei memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</hi> And ſo praying the moſt High to bleſſe our good proceedings and well intended inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours with happie &amp; proſperous ſucceſſe to his glorie, the good of his Church our owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and the converſion (if it may be) or elſe the confuſion of his and our enemies; <hi>I</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with this my laſt requeſt, that ſuch obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate &amp; ſtiffe-necked Papiſts, as will not be yoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked or reclaimed from their groſſe &amp; abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable idolatries and wicked ſuperſtitions, but ſtill like Swine ſwill and ſwell themſelues with the filthie dregs, that the great whore of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh <hi>Babilon</hi> giveth vnto them, refuſing to be cured by the healthie and wholſome potion of Gods moſt holie truth, may not bee ſuffred to dwell together with mee in this land; for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it lawfull for ſuch to liue amidſt Gods choſen Heritage, to defile the Land with their filthines, nor (if they ſhould) can my life bee without continuall hazard and danger, by their ſecret and villainous attempts. Call vpon thy
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15710:25"/>
King therefore, to execute iuſtice &amp; iudgment in cutting off theſe workers of iniquitie, whoſe religion is rebellion, whoſe faith is faction, whoſe pietie is wicked pollicie and practiſe of murdring both ſoules &amp; bodies of Kings, and all eſtates of people, and to roote and rid them cleane out of the confines and limits of thy whole Monarchie, which being clearely pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of them, may ever heereafter growe vp, proſper, and flouriſh in quiet ſafetie, ſound health, and invincible ſtrength in everie mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the whole bodie of all true and truly devoted ſubiects, with their righteous and religious Head and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</p>
            <trailer>Deo ſoli gratia &amp; laus.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
